Guide to the Sean Sweeney Collection of Irish Northern Aid Ephemera AIA.072
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sean Sweeney Collection of Irish Northern Aid Ephemera
1980-2012
1980-1991
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sweeney, Sean
AIA.072
2.25 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 1 oversize flat box, 1 artifact box, and 2 oversize folders in shared boxes
Sean Sweeney was an active member of the mid-Manhattan branch of the Irish Northern Aid Committee (Noraid), often participating in demonstrations in front of the British Embassy in an effort to raise awareness about the Troubles in Northern Ireland. He collected the materials that comprise this collection throughout the course of his activism and engagement with other Irish American political organizations in the late 20th century. The 1981 hunger strikes by Irish republican prisoners in the H-Blocks of Long Kesh prison and the Armagh Women's Prison are heavily documented by calendars, flyers announcing demonstrations, and posters memorializing the deceased. The collection also demonstrates the varied media coverage of domestic republican activism and conflict in Northern Ireland from multiple viewpoints, including physical force republicanism, nonviolent advocacy, and mainstream American media outlets through numerous newspaper and newsletter publications.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Sean Sweeney in June 2014. The accession number associated with this gift is 2014.141.
Related Archival Materials
Frank Durkan Papers (AIA 008)
George Harrison Papers (AIA 009)
Archives of Irish American Irish Republicanism Collection (AIA 022)
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of flyers, newspapers, newsletters, memoranda, correspondence, and various artifacts sold or distributed at demonstrations documenting Irish republicanism activism in New York City during the late 20th century. The collection consists of materials produced in both Ireland and the United States, although the majority of the collection documents the activities of the mid-Manhattan chapter of the Irish Northern Aid Committee (Noraid), an Irish American organization dedicated to fund raising and promoting public awareness of the Troubles in Northern Ireland. The collection also contains other materials collected by Sean Sweeney in the course of his activism, including items from other Irish activist and political groups, including Sinn Fein and the Political Education Committee of Action Irish. The 1981 hunger strikes by Irish republican prisoners in the H-Blocks of Long Kesh prison and the Armagh Women's Prison are heavily documented by calendars, flyers announcing demonstrations, and posters memorializing the deceased, including many drawn by Irish Echo artist Brian Mór Ó Baoighill. The collection also demonstrates the varied media coverage of domestic republican activism and conflict in Northern Ireland from multiple viewpoints, including physical force republicanism, nonviolent advocacy, and mainstream American media outlets through numerous newspaper and newsletter publications.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically.
Historical/Biographical Note
Sean Sweeney was an active member of the mid-Manhattan branch of the Irish Northern Aid Committee (Noraid), often participating in demonstrations in front of the British Embassy in an effort to raise awareness about the Troubles in Northern Ireland, with specific emphasis on the 1981 hunger strikes. He collected the materials in this collection throughout the course of his activism and engagement with other Irish American political organizations in the late 20th century.
Human rights -- Northern Ireland.; Hunger strikes -- Northern Ireland.; Northern Ireland -- History -- 1969-1994.; Violence -- Northern Ireland.; Irish Americans -- New York (State) -- New York -- Political activity.; Irish Americans -- Politics and government.; Irish Northern Aid Committee; Sinn Fein
- An Phoblacht, Feb 1982-Jul 1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- An Phoblacht, Aug 1982-Mar 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- An Phoblacht, Apr 1983-Jun 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- An Phoblacht, Feb 1987-Dec 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Ballads and Folk Songs, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bumper Stickers, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- The Captive Voice (An Glor Gafa), 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Counter Spy, Jun 1983-Aug 1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- February 20th Committee (Washington, D.C. Demonstration), undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Hunger Strike Posters, circa 1981 (Box Tamiment Shared AIAXOS001, Folder 3)
- Iris, Jul 1982-Dec 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Iris, Jul 1985-Sep 1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Irish America, Jun 1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Irish Northern Aid Committee: Collection Can, circa 1982-1990 (Box 2)
- Irish Northern Aid Committee: Hunger Strike Defense Fund, after 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Irish Northern Aid Committee: Irish Prisoners of War Committee, after 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Irish Northern Aid Commitee: Membership Card, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- The Irish People, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Irish Republicanism Posters, circa 1978-1990 (Box Tamiment Shared AIAXOS001, Folder 4)
- Letter from Mayor Ed Koch, Mar 8, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Life, Oct 1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- National Geographic, Apr 1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- New York H-Block / Armagh Committee, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Overthrow, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Political Education Committee Newsletter (Action Irish), 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Republican Resistance Calendars (Feilire Poblactanac), 1986-1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Saoirse Irish Freedom, Aug 1991 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- "They Shoot Children: The Use of Rubber and Plastic Bullets in the North of Ireland", 1982 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- "This Baby is Being Body-Searched in Armagh..." (Sinn Fein POW Department), circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Time, Jan 11, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- T-shirts, circa 1980-1990 (Box 3)
- Wallet, circa 1982-1990 (Box 2)
- WIN (Workshop in Nonviolence), Aug 1981 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- The Writings of Bobby Sands, 1954-1981, May 1981 (Box 1, Folder 30)